Guide to the Agricultural Research Center Washington State Commodity Commission Reports 1976-2011
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Agricultural Research Center Washington State Commodity Commission Reports
1976-2011
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 361
Washington State University. Agricultural Research Center
8 Linear feet of shelf space 20 Boxes
Washington State University agricultural project proposals hoping for research funding from state commodity commissions, as well as research progress reports for the funded projects.
The Washington State University Agriculture Research Center (ARC) is a part of WSU’s College of Agricultural, Human, and Natural Resource Sciences (CAHNRS). The ARC began in 1892 as the Washington Agricultural Experiment Station, then an element of the Washington Agricultural College, Experiment Station, and School of Science, now Washington State University. Located near Pullman on a farm donated to the state, the station became the site of agricultural instruction and experimental work conducted by the staff of the station and the faculty of the College of Agriculture. It soon extended to branch stations across the state. In 1946 it became part of the Institute of Agricultural Sciences, and in 1965 it was integrated into the newly-organized Agricultural Research Center (ARC) of the College of Agriculture.
Washington State’s commodity commissions are “industry-funded state agencies that promote and fund crop research and/or the marketing of crops.” The commissions are considered governmental agencies as they are state-mandated, but they are governed and funded by growers under the supervision of the state Director of Agriculture. The oldest Washington commodity commission, the Washington Apple Commission, dates to 1937.
The collection consists primarily of research proposals for agricultural projects seeking funding, and then of research progress reports for funded projects. Usually both the proposals and progress reports for a given year are combined in one document. Documents date from 1976 to 2011. Each report is addressed to one of the Washington State commodity commissions; a very few series may be addressed to other commissions.
The research covered in these documents generally comes from subsidiary departments to Washington State University’s College of Agriculture (later CAHE, still later CAHNRS).
Materials are arranged alphabetically in series by the agricultural commodity covered in each report. A few series contain other types of reports besides the proposal and progress reports; those other report types will be in a subseries after the proposal and progress documents. Within all these subseries, materials are ordered chronologically. At the end of the larger series are a few small series which are not limited to one specific commodity; these are arranged by the committee they report to.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The majority of the documents in this collection were donated by the Washington State University Agricultural Research Center (ARC) to the WSU Libraries’ Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections (MASC) on July 28, 2011, and accessioned as UA2011-09. An ongoing file reorganization project in the ARC meant a slow steady stream of these continued coming in to MASC through April of 2015, when the project finished. All these materials were treated as part of the one initial accession (UA2011-09). Some materials from this accession were filed in the WSU Publications collections, and one small set of loose papers related to Horse Heaven Irrigation will be processed separately.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington State University. Agricultural Research Center
Proposal writing for grants
Agriculture; Colleges and Universities
- Apples. Includes some Cherries. For the Washington Tree Fruit Research Commission. For the WTFRC and/or the Columbia River Orchards Foundation. For the CROF.
  - New Tree Fruit Research Proposals (WTFRC and CROF)
    - 1982 (Box 1, Item 1)
    - 1983 (Box 1, Item 2)
    - 1984 (Box 1, Item 3)
  - New Tree Fruit Research Proposals (WTFRC and CROF)
    - 1982 (Box 1, Item 4)
    - 1983 (Box 1, Item 5)
  - New Tree Fruit Research Proposals (WTFRC and CROF)
    - 1982 (Box 1, Item 6)
    - 1983 (Box 1, Item 7)
    - 1984 (Box 1, Item 8)
    - 1986 (Box 1, Item 9)
    - 1987 (Box 1, Item 10)
  - New Tree Fruit Research Proposals (WTFRC and CROF)
    - 1988 (Box 1, Item 11)
    - 1989 (Box 1, Item 12)
    - 1990 (Box 1, Item 13)
  - New Tree Fruit Research Proposals (WTFRC and CROF)
    - 1991 (Box 1, Item 14)
    - 1992 (Box 1, Item 15)
    - 1993 (Box 1, Item 16)
    - 1994 (Box 1, Item 17)
    - 1996 (Box 2, Item 1)
    - 1997 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - New Tree Fruit Research Proposals (WTFRC and CROF)
    - 1996 (Box 2, Item 3)
    - 1997 (Box 2, Item 4)
    - 1999 (Box 2, Item 5)
    - 2000 (Box 2, Item 6)
    - 2001 (Box 2, Item 7)
    - 2002 (Box 2, Item 8)
    - 2003 (Box 2, Item 9)
    - 2004 (Box 2, Item 10)
    - 2005 (Box 2, Item 11)
  - New Tree Fruit Research Proposals (WTFRC and CROF)
    - 2001 (Box 3, Item 1)
    - 2002 (Box 3, Item 2)
    - 2003 (Box 3, Item 3)
    - 2004 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - New Tree Fruit Research Proposals (WTFRC and CROF)
    - 1997 (Box 3, Item 5)
    - 2002 (Box 3, Item 6)
    - 2003 (Box 3, Item 7)
- Aquaculture.
  - Progress Reports
    - 2003 (Box 3, Item 8)
    - 2005 (Box 3, Item 9)
    - 2006 (Box 3, Item 10)
- Asparagus. For the Washington Asparagus Industry Irrevocable Research Trust, later the Washington Asparagus Commission.
  - Reports and Proposals (WAIIRT)
    - 1982 (Box 3, Item 11)
    - 1984 (Box 3, Item 12)
    - 1985 (Box 3, Item 13)
    - 1986 (Box 3, Item 14)
    - 1987 (Box 3, Item 15)
    - 1989 (Box 3, Item 16)
    - 1991 (Box 3, Item 17)
    - 1992 (Box 3, Item 18)
    - 1994 (Box 3, Item 19)
    - 1995 (Box 3, Item 20)
    - 1996 (Box 3, Item 21)
    - 1997 (Box 3, Item 22)
    - 1998 (Box 3, Item 23)
    - 1999 (Box 3, Item 24)
- Barley. For the Washington Barley Commission.
  - Barley Research Review
    - 1986 (Box 4, Item 1)
    - 1987 (Box 4, Item 2)
    - 1988 (Box 4, Item 3)
    - 1989 (Box 4, Item 4)
    - 1990 (Box 4, Item 5)
    - 1991 (Box 4, Item 6)
    - 1992 (Box 4, Item 7)
    - 1993 (Box 4, Item 8)
    - 1994 (Box 4, Item 9)
    - 1995 (Box 4, Item 10)
    - 1996 (Box 4, Item 11)
    - 1997 (Box 4, Item 12)
    - 1998 (Box 4, Item 13)
    - 1999 (Box 4, Item 14)
    - 2000 (Box 4, Item 15)
    - 2001 (Box 4, Item 16)
    - 2002 (Box 4, Item 17)
    - 2003 (Box 4, Item 18)
    - 2004 (Box 4, Item 19)
    - 2005 (Box 4, Item 20)
    - 2006 (Box 4, Item 21)
    - 2008 (Box 4, Item 22)
- Beef. For the Washington Cattlemen's Association and the Washington State Beef Commission.
  - Research Program Summary
    - 1984 (Box 5, Item 1)
    - 1985 (Box 5, Item 2)
- Blueberries. For the Washington State Blueberry Commission.
  - Blueberry Research Proposals and Project Reports
    - 1984 (Box 5, Item 3)
    - 1985 (Box 5, Item 4)
    - 1986 (Box 5, Item 5)
    - 1987 (Box 5, Item 6)
    - 1988 (Box 5, Item 7)
    - 1989 (Box 5, Item 8)
    - 1990 (Box 5, Item 9)
    - 1991 (Box 5, Item 10)
    - 1993 (Box 5, Item 11)
    - 1994 (Box 5, Item 12)
    - 1997 (Box 5, Item 13)
    - 1998 (Box 5, Item 14)
    - 2005 (Box 5, Item 15)
- Cherries. For the Washington State Tree Fruit Research Commission, later the WSTFRC and the Oregon Sweet Cherry Commission.
  - Cherry Research Review [and Plans]
    - 1991 (Box 5, Item 16)
    - 1992 (Box 5, Item 17)
  - Progress Reports to Agricultural Research Foundation for the Oregon Sweet Cherry Commission
    - 1993-1994 (Box 5, Item 18)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 5, Item 19)
  - Cherry Research Review [and Plans]
    - 1994 (Box 5, Item 20)
    - 1995 (Box 5, Item 21)
    - 1996 (Box 5, Item 22)
    - 1997 (Box 5, Item 23)
    - 1998 (Box 5, Item 24)
    - 1999 (Box 5, Item 25)
    - 2000 (Box 5, Item 26)
  - Northwest Cherry Research Review [and Plans]
    - 2001 (Item 27)
    - 2002 (Box 6, Item 1)
    - 2003 (Box 6, Item 2)
  - Cherry and Soft Fruit Research Review [and Plans], 2004 (Box 6, Item 3)
  - Cherry Research Review [and Plans], 2005 (Box 6, Item 4)
- Cranberries. For the Washington State Cranberry Commission.
  - Cranberry Research Proposals and Project Reports
    - 1984 (Box 6, Item 5)
    - 1985 (Box 6, Item 6)
    - 1986 (Box 6, Item 7)
    - 1987 (Box 6, Item 8)
    - 1988 (Box 6, Item 9)
    - 1989 (Box 6, Item 10)
    - 1990 (Box 6, Item 11)
    - 1991 (Box 6, Item 12)
    - 1992 (Box 6, Item 13)
    - 1993 (Box 6, Item 14)
    - 1994 (Box 6, Item 15)
    - 1995 (Box 6, Item 16)
    - 1996 (Box 6, Item 17)
    - 1997 (Box 6, Item 18)
    - 1998 (Box 6, Item 19)
    - 2000 (Box 6, Item 20)
    - 2001 (Box 6, Item 21)
    - 2002 (Box 6, Item 22)
    - 2004 (Box 6, Item 23)
    - 2005 (Box 6, Item 24)
- Dairy. For the Washington State Dairy Products Committee.
  - Research Proposals and Progress Reports
    - 1982 (Box 7, Item 1)
    - 1983 (Box 7, Item 2)
    - 1984 (Box 7, Item 3)
    - 1986 (Box 7, Item 4)
    - 1987 (Box 7, Item 5)
    - 1988 (Box 7, Item 6)
    - 1989 (Box 7, Item 7)
    - 1990 (Box 7, Item 8)
    - 1991 (Box 7, Item 9)
    - 1992 (Box 7, Item 10)
    - 1994 (Box 7, Item 11)
    - 1995 (Box 7, Item 12)
    - 1996 (Box 7, Item 13)
    - 1998 (Box 7, Item 14)
    - 1999 (Box 7, Item 15)
    - 2005 (Box 7, Item 16)
  - Progress Reports, 2006 (Box 7, Item 17)
  - Proposals, 2006 (Box 7, Item 18)
- Grapes, Concord. For the Washington State Concord Grape Research Council.
  - Reports and Proposals
    - 1985 (Box 7, Item 19)
    - 1986 (Box 7, Item 20)
    - 1990 (Box 7, Item 21)
    - 1991 (Box 7, Item 22)
    - 1992 (Box 7, Item 23)
    - 1995 (Box 7, Item 24)
    - 1996 (Box 7, Item 25)
- Grapes, Wine. For the Washington Wine Grape Advisory Committee.
  - Wine Grape Research Program (Proposal), 1980 (Box 8, Item 1)
  - Reports and Proposals
    - 1985 (Box 8, Item 2)
    - 1987 (Box 8, Item 3)
    - 1988 (Box 8, Item 4)
    - 1989 (Box 8, Item 5)
    - 1990 (Box 8, Item 6)
    - 1991 (Box 8, Item 7)
    - 1992 (Box 8, Item 8)
    - 1993 (Box 8, Item 9)
    - 1999 (Box 8, Item 10)
    - 2000 (Box 8, Item 11)
    - 2006 (Box 8, Item 12)
- Grass Seed. For the Grass Seed Cropping Systems for a Sustainable Agriculture (GSCSSA).
  - Progress Reports
    - 1993 (Box 8, Item 13)
    - 1994 (Box 8, Item 14)
    - 1995 (Box 8, Item 15)
    - 1996 (Box 8, Item 16)
    - 1997 (Box 8, Item 17)
    - 1998 (Box 8, Item 18)
    - 1999 (Box 8, Item 19)
    - 2000 (Box 8, Item 20)
    - 2001 (Box 8, Item 21)
    - 2002 (Box 8, Item 22)
    - 2003 (Box 8, Item 23)
    - 2004 (Box 9, Item 1)
    - 2005 (Box 9, Item 2)
    - 2006 (Box 9, Item 3)
    - 2009 (Box 9, Item 4)
    - 2010 (Box 9, Item 5)
- Hops. For the Hop Research Council.
  - Reports and Proposals
    - 1982 (Box 9, Item 6)
    - 1983 (Box 9, Item 7)
    - 1984 (Box 9, Item 8)
    - 1985 (Box 9, Item 9)
    - 1986 (Box 9, Item 10)
    - 1987 (Box 9, Item 11)
    - 1988 (Box 9, Item 12)
    - 1989 (Box 9, Item 13)
    - 1990 (Box 9, Item 14)
    - 1991 (Box 9, Item 15)
    - 1992 (Box 9, Item 16)
  - Reports (IAREC only), 1994 (Box 9, Item 17)
  - Reports, 1995 (Box 9, Item 18)
  - Reports (IAREC only), 1996 (Box 9, Item 19)
  - Reports, 1999 (Box 9, Item 20)
- Mint. For the Washington Mint Commission.
  - Report and Proposals
    - 1982 (Box 10, Item 1)
    - 1983 (Box 10, Item 2)
    - 1984 (Box 10, Item 3)
    - 1987 (Box 10, Item 4)
    - 1988 (Box 10, Item 5)
    - 1989 (Box 10, Item 6)
    - 1990 (Box 10, Item 7)
    - 1991 (Box 10, Item 8)
    - 1992 (Box 10, Item 9)
    - 1994 (Box 10, Item 10)
    - 1995 (Box 10, Item 11)
    - 1996 (Box 10, Item 12)
    - 1997 (Box 10, Item 13)
    - 1998 (Box 10, Item 14)
- Onions
  - Report to the Walla Wall Sweet Onion Growers Association, 1991 (Box 10, Item 15)
- Peas and Lentils. For the Washington Dry Pea and Lentil Commission.
  - Research Progress and Plans
    - 1981 (Box 10, Item 16)
    - 1983 (Box 10, Item 17)
    - 1985 (Box 10, Item 18)
    - 1986 (Box 10, Item 19)
    - 1987 (Box 10, Item 20)
    - 1988 (Box 10, Item 21)
    - 1989 (Box 10, Item 22)
    - 1990 (Box 10, Item 23)
    - 1992 (Box 10, Item 24)
    - 1996 (Box 10, Item 25)
    - 1997 (Box 10, Item 26)
    - 1998 (Box 10, Item 27)
    - 1999 (Box 10, Item 28)
    - 2000 (Box 10, Item 29)
  - Field Experiments on Dry Pea, Lentil, Chickpea, and Austrian Winter Pea
    - 1995 (Box 10, Item 30)
    - 1999 (Box 10, Item 31)
- Pears. For the Washington State Tree Fruit Research Commission and the Winter Pear Control Committee.
  - Research Review [and Plans for Projects]
    - 1987 (Box 11, Item 1)
    - 1988 (Box 11, Item 2)
    - 1989 (Box 11, Item 3)
    - 1990 (Box 11, Item 4)
    - 1991 (Box 11, Item 5)
    - 1992 (Box 11, Item 6)
    - 1993 (Box 11, Item 7)
    - 1994 (Box 11, Item 8)
    - 1996 (Box 11, Item 9)
    - 1997 (Box 11, Item 10)
    - 1998 (Box 11, Item 11)
    - 2000 (Box 11, Item 12)
    - 2002 (Box 11, Item 13)
    - 2004 (Box 11, Item 14)
- Potatoes. For the Washington Potato Commission.
  - Research Review: Proposals
    - 1993 (Box 11, Item 15)
    - 1997 (Box 11, Item 16)
    - 1998 (Box 11, Item 17)
    - 1999 (Box 11, Item 18)
    - 2000 (Box 12, Item 1)
    - 2001 (Box 12, Item 2)
    - 2002 (Box 12, Item 3)
    - 2003 (Box 12, Item 4)
    - 2004 (Box 12, Item 5)
    - 2006 (Box 12, Item 6)
    - 2007 (Box 12, Item 7)
  - Research Review: Progress Reports
    - 1994 (Box 12, Item 8)
    - 1998 (Box 12, Item 9)
    - 1999 (Box 12, Item 10)
    - 2000 (Box 12, Item 11)
    - 2001 (Box 12, Item 12)
    - 2002 (Box 13, Item 1)
    - 2003 (Box 13, Item 2)
    - 2004 (Box 13, Item 3)
    - 2005 (Box 13, Item 4)
    - 2006 (Box 13, Item 5)
  - Potato Cultivar Evaluation
    - 1987 (Box 13, Item 6)
    - 1992 (Box 13, Item 7)
    - 1993 (Box 13, Item 8)
    - 1995 (Box 13, Item 9)
    - 1997 (Box 13, Item 10)
    - 1999 (Box 13, Item 11)
    - 2001 (Box 13, Item 12)
- Raspberries. For the Washington State Red Raspberry Commission and Washington Red Raspberry Growers Association.
  - Research Proposals and Progress Reports
    - 1985 (Box 14, Item 1)
    - 1986 (Box 14, Item 2)
    - 1987 (Box 14, Item 3)
    - 1988 (Box 14, Item 4)
    - 1989 (Box 14, Item 5)
    - 1990 (Box 14, Item 6)
    - 1991 (Box 14, Item 7)
    - 1992 (Box 14, Item 8)
    - 1993 (Box 14, Item 9)
    - 1994 (Box 14, Item 10)
    - 1995 (Box 14, Item 11)
    - 1988 (Box 14, Item 12)
    - 1999 (Box 14, Item 13)
    - 2002 (Box 14, Item 14)
    - 2005 (Box 14, Item 15)
    - 2007 (Box 14, Item 16)
    - 2009 (Box 14, Item 17)
    - 2010 (Box 14, Item 18)
- Strawberries. For the Washington State Strawberry Commission.
  - Research Proposals and Progress Reports
    - 1985 (Box 15, Item 1)
    - 1987 (Box 15, Item 2)
    - 1990 (Box 15, Item 3)
    - 1991 (Box 15, Item 4)
    - 1992 (Box 15, Item 5)
    - 1993 (Box 15, Item 6)
    - 1994 (Box 15, Item 7)
    - 1995 (Box 15, Item 8)
    - 1998 (Box 15, Item 9)
    - 1999 (Box 15, Item 10)
    - 2000 (Box 15, Item 11)
    - 2001 (Box 15, Item 12)
    - 2002 (Box 15, Item 13)
    - 2003 (Box 15, Item 14)
    - 2005 (Box 15, Item 15)
- Wheat. For the Washington Wheat Commission, Washington Association of Wheat Growers, and the Hay and Grain Fund Advisory Committee.
  - Research Review
    - 1976 (Box 15, Item 16)
    - 1979 (Box 15, Item 17)
    - 1981 (Box 15, Item 18)
  - New Proposals, 1982 (Box 15, Item 19)
  - Research Progress and Plans
    - 1982 (Box 15, Item 20)
    - 1983 (Box 15, Item 21)
    - 1984 (Box 15, Item 22)
    - 1986 (Box 15, Item 23)
    - 1987 (Box 15, Item 24)
    - 1988 (Box 15, Item 25)
    - 1989 (Box 16, Item 1)
    - 1990 (Box 16, Item 2)
    - 1991 (Box 16, Item 3)
    - 1992 (Box 16, Item 4)
    - 1993 (Box 16, Item 5)
    - 1994 (Box 16, Item 6)
    - 1996 (Box 16, Item 7)
    - 1999 (Box 16, Item 8)
    - 2001 (Box 16, Item 9)
    - 2002 (Box 16, Item 10)
    - 2003 (Box 16, Item 11)
  - Research Progress and Plans: Progress Reports, 2005 (Box 17, Item 1)
  - Research Progress and Plans: Proposals, 2005 (Box 17, Item 2)
  - Research Progress and Plans, 2006 (Box 17, Item 3)
  - Research Progress and Plans: Progress Reports, 2007 (Box 17, Item 4)
  - Research Progress and Plans: Proposals, 2007 (Box 17, Item 5)
  - Research Progress and Plans, 2008 (Box 17, Item 6)
  - Research Review (Wheat and Barley)
    - 2010 (Box 17, Item 7)
    - 2011 (Box 17, Item 8)
  - Results from Cooperative Wheat Varietal Experiements in the Western Regions
    - 1995 (Box 18, Item 1)
    - 1996 (Box 18, Item 2)
    - 1997 (Box 18, Item 3)
    - 1998 (Box 18, Item 4)
    - 1999 (Box 18, Item 5)
    - 2000 (Box 18, Item 6)
    - 2001 (Box 18, Item 7)
    - 2002 (Box 18, Item 8)
- Wheat, threats to: Jointed Goatgrass. For the National Jointed Goatgrass Research Program.
  - Progress Reports, Final Reports, and Funded Proposals
    - 1996 (Box 18, Item 9)
    - 1997 (Box 18, Item 10)
    - 1998 (Box 18, Item 11)
    - 1999 (Box 18, Item 12)
    - 2000 (Box 18, Item 13)
    - 2001 (Box 19, Item 1)
    - 2002 (Box 19, Item 2)
    - 2003 (Box 19, Item 3)
    - 2004 (Box 19, Item 4)
    - 2005 (Box 19, Item 5)
    - 2006 (Box 19, Item 6)
    - 2007 (Box 19, Item 7)
- Northwest Columbia Plateau Wind Erosion / Air Quality Project.
  - Annual Reports
    - 1998 (Box 19, Item 8)
    - 1999 (Box 19, Item 9)
    - 2000 (Box 19, Item 10)
    - 2001 (Box 19, Item 11)
    - 2002 (Box 19, Item 12)
    - 2003 (Box 19, Item 13)
    - 2004 (Box 20, Item 1)
    - 2006 (Box 20, Item 2)
    - 2008 (Box 20, Item 3)
- Northwest Agriculture Research Foundation and Affiliated Organizations.
  - Progress Reports and Research Proposals
    - 1997 (Box 20, Item 4)
    - 2001 (Box 20, Item 5)
    - 2002 (Box 20, Item 6)
    - 2004 (Box 20, Item 7)
    - 2005 (Box 20, Item 8)
- Washington Tree Fruit Commission and the Hood River Shipper Grower Association.
  - Research and Education Reports and Proposals, 1992 (Box 20, Item 9)
- Western Washington Tree Fruit Research Foundation.
  - Proposals and Reports, 1992 (Box 20, Item 10)
- CSRS Report of Research Activities to Livestock Industries.
  - Beef and Dairy Cattle, 1982-1988 (Box 20, Item 11)
  - Horses, 1982-1988 (Box 20, Item 12)
  - Poultry, 1982-1988 (Box 20, Item 13)
  - Sheep and Goats, 1982-1988 (Box 20, Item 14)
  - Swine, 1982-1988 (Box 20, Item 15)